Register of the Archives of the Soviet communist party and Soviet state microfilm collection: Russian State Archive of Contemporary History (Rossiiskii gosudarstvennyi arkhiv noveishei istorii - RGANI)
Hoover Institution Archives
- Fond 89, Communist Party of the Soviet Union on Trial records, 1919-1992; 24 reels (Reel 1.989-1.1012)
  - Opis 57
    - Memorandum to J. Stalin from A. Kozlov, Chief of the Agricultural Department, reporting on implementing the TsK VKP(b) resolution of May 30, 1950, On Amalgamation of Small Collective Farms and on the Related Tasks of Party Organizations, with cover letter to Stalin from G. Malenkov, 1950 July (Opis 57, Reel 1.1008, File 5)
    - Resolution of the USSR Council of Ministers re forced transfer of individual farms and land plots from private ownership to the ownership of collective farms and re individual farmers forced to join the collective farms in the Volynskaia, Drogobychskaia, Lvovskaia, Rovenskaia, Stanislavskaia, Ternopolskaia, Chernovitskaia, and Izmailskaia oblasts of the Ukraine, 1950 July (Opis 57, Reel 1.1008, File 6)
    - Extract from the minutes of the VKP(b) Politburo approving a telegram to VKP(b) committees in oblasts and krais and to central committees of communist parties of the union republics re preservation of livestock in the process of amalgamating small collective farms; the telegram from J. Stalin warning against the slaughter of communal livestock in the process of amalgamating small collective farms, 1950 July (Opis 57, Reel 1.1008, File 7)
    - Extract from the minutes of the VKP(b) Secretariat asking that the Politburo approve a draft telegram to be sent to VKP(b) committees in oblasts and krais and to central committees of communist parties of the union republics re preservation of livestock during the process of amalgamating small collective farms; the draft telegram warning against the slaughter of communal livestock in the process of amalgamating small collective farms, 1950 July (Opis 57, Reel 1.1008, File 8)
    - Extract from the minutes of the VKP(b) Politburo designating a commission for designing a TsK document on tasks related to amalgamation of small collective farms, 1951 March (Opis 57, Reel 1.1008, File 9)
    - Personal letter to J. Stalin from N. Khrushchev containing Khrushchev's acknowledgment of his mistakes in response to Stalin's criticism of his speech On Building and Improvement of Collective Farms and proposing to prepare another publication with self-criticism (with Stalin's handwritten annotation sending the letter to the TsK archives), 1951 March (Opis 57, Reel 1.1008, File 10)
    - Extract from the minutes of the VKP(b) Politburo approving the text of a secret letter from the TsK VKP(b) to the central committees of union republics, VKP(b) committees in krais, oblasts, cities, okrugs, and raions On the Tasks for Building Collective Farms with Respect to Amalgamation of Small Collective Farms; the secret letter, 1951 April (Opis 57, Reel 1.1008, File 11)
    - Extract from the minutes of the VKP(b) Politburo approving a request from local party organs to familiarize communists with the secret letter On the Tasks for Building Collective Farms with Respect to Amalgamation of Small Collective Farms, 1951 April (Opis 57, Reel 1.1008, File 12)
    - Extract from the minutes of the VKP(b) Secretariat asking that the Politburo approve a request from local party organs to familiarize communists with the secret letter On the Tasks for Building Collective Farms with Respect to Amalgamation of Small Collective Farms, 1951 April (Opis 57, Reel 1.1008, File 13)
    - Extract from the minutes of the TsK KPSS Presidium canceling the secret letter from the TsK VKP(b) On the Tasks for Building Collective Farms with Respect to Amalgamation of Small Collective Farms; draft resolution of the TsK KPSS; brief note dispatching material to members and candidate members of the TsK KPSS Presidium; draft resolution of the TsK KPSS signed by V. Ignatov, IE. Furtseva, and P. Pospelov, 1958 March-April (Opis 57, Reel 1.1008, File 14)
    - Extract from the minutes of the VKP(b) Politburo relating to the harvest and procurement of agricultural products in 1952, denouncing the collective farm practice of distributing among collective farmers what was left from the harvest after state procurement before creating seed, fodder grain, insurance stocks, and other communal stocks, and directing that the collective farms change this practice, 1952 July (Opis 57, Reel 1.1008, File 15)
    - Extract from the minutes of the VKP(b) Politburo approving, with amendments, draft resolutions of the People's Commissariat of Agriculture (Narkomzem) on calculation in work-days [unit of payment in collective farms] of different types of agricultural work and on the approximate rate of output for 1933, and putting the Narkomzem and Agricultural Department of the TsK VKP(b) in charge of improving regulations on agricultural work, of taking stock of expenses, labor resources, and number of work-days per household and per different kind of agricultural work in different regions; said two draft resolutions of the Narkomzem; memorandum to the [VKP(b)] Politburo and J. Stalin from L. Kaganovich and IA. Yakovlev requesting approval of the draft resolution of the Narkomzem, 1933 February-March (Opis 57, Reel 1.1008, File 16)
    - Extract from the minutes of the VKP(b) Politburo approving a draft resolution of the USSR Council of People's Commissars (Sovnarkom) and the TsK VKP(b) on the procedure for creating grain stock for collective farms and for distribution of grain among collective farmers; the draft resolution regulating the procedure for creating seed stock, insurance stock, and fodder grain stock and for distribution of seed among collective farmers, 1933 August (Opis 57, Reel 1.1008, File 17)
      See also file 15 of this opis.
    - Extract from the minutes of the VKP(b) Politburo clarifying the procedure for distribution of the work-days among collective farmers in 1933 and 1934, 1933 August (Opis 57, Reel 1.1008, File 18)
    - Memorandum to the TsK VKP(b) and J. Stalin and to the USSR Soviet of People's Commissars from A. Vyshinskii, USSR Prosecutor General, re regulations for child labor in collective farms, 1939 March (Opis 57, Reel 1.1008, File 19)
    - Memorandum to J. Stalin from L. Beria re reports on the lack of food supplies in Moldavia, Izmailskaia oblast of the Ukraine, and Voronezhskaia and Stalingradskaia oblasts and re complaints obtained by the Ministry of State Security (MGB) through secret inspection of private letters of oblasts' population; report to V. Abakumov, USSR Minister of State Security, from Mordovets, Minister of State Security of Moldavia, on the cases of dystrophy, atrophy, and swelling (totaling 10,834) caused by insufficient food supply in some areas of Moldavia; special report to V. Abakumov from Savchenko, Minister of State Security of the Ukraine, re insufficient food supply, famine, and several death cases among residents of Tarutinskii and Borodinskii raions of Izmailskaia oblast of the Ukraine; list of excerpts from letters mailed by the population of Voronezhskaia and Stalingradskaia oblasts complaining of inadequate food resulting in swelling and diseases, 1946 November-December (Opis 57, Reel 1.1008, File 20)
    - Cover letter to L. Beria and Andreev from J. Stalin, accompanying an amended resolution of the USSR Council of Ministers and the TsK VKP(b) and requesting that the resolution and an old resolution of 1939 be published in the press as soon as possible; the resolution of the TsK VKP(b) on the measures to avoid violation of the Code of Agricultural Society (Artel) in collective farms; resolution of the USSR Council of Ministers and the TsK VKP(b); draft resolution of the TsK VKP(b) with handwritten amendments; draft resolution of the USSR Council of Ministers and the TsK VKP(b) with handwritten amendments, 1946 September (Opis 57, Reel 1.1008, File 21)
    - Memorandum to L. Beria from J. Stalin directing that Beria send him a draft resolution of the TsK KPSS banning the raise in salaries and that the resolution be formulated in a strong manner; Stalin's holograph memorandum, 1946 September (Opis 57, Reel 1.1008, File 22)
  - Opis 58
    - Cover letter to J. Stalin from V. Potemkin, Deputy Commissar of Foreign Affairs, accompanying a memorandum of his conversation with Grzibowski, Polish Ambassador to the USSR; memorandum of the meeting between V. Potemkin and Grzibowski, in which V. Potemkin handed Grzibowski a note from V. Molotov; clipping from Pravda (Truth) newspaper no. 259 of September 18, 1939, with the note, 1939 September (Opis 58, Reel 1.1008, File 1)
    - Extract from the minutes of the TsK VKP(b) Politburo approving a resolution of the Defense Committee on the introduction of martial law for escort troops of the People's Commissariat of Internal Affairs (NKVD) in Belorussian, Kiev, and Leningrad military districts and directing that all stations in the Belorussian and Kiev districts and all distribution camps in the cities of Kozelsk (Belorussia) and Putivl (Ukraine) with prisoners of war be guarded by NKVD escort troops; memorandum to V. Molotov, Chairman of the Council of People's Commissars, from L. Beria, People's Commissar of Internal Affairs; resolution of the Defense Committee, 1939 September (Opis 58, Reel 1.1008, File 2)
    - Extract from the minutes of the TsK VKP(b) Politburo approving proposals put forth by L. Mekhlis and L. Beria re treatment and accommodations of prisoners of war of different nationalities and different ranks; draft resolution on prisoners of war, with cover letter to A. Zhdanov from L. Beria and L. Mekhlis (with their signatures), 1939 October (Opis 58, Reel 1.1008, File 3)
    - Memorandum to the TsK VKP(b) and J. Stalin from L. Beria and L. Mekhlis containing their proposals re prisoners of war, with signatures of Stalin, A. Mikoian, K. Voroshilov, V. Molotov, L. Kaganovich, and A. Zhdanov confirming their approval (with amendments) of the proposals, 1939 October (Opis 58, Reel 1.1008, File 4)
      See also file 3 of this opis.
    - Memorandum to the USSR Council of People's Commissars and V. Molotov from L. Beria, People's Commissar of Internal Affairs, containing Beria's proposals re the procedure for handing over to German authorities 33,000 Polish prisoners of war who were residents of the portion of Poland occupied by Germany (approved by V. Molotov, K. Voroshilov, A. Mikoian, Andreev, L. Kaganovich, A. Zhdanov, and M. Kalinin), 1939 October (Opis 58, Reel 1.1008, File 5)
    - Extract from the minutes of the TsK VKP(b) Politburo approving L. Beria's proposals re procedure for handing over to German authorities 33,000 Polish prisoners of war who were residents of the part of Poland occupied by Germany, 1939 October (Opis 58, Reel 1.1008, File 6)
    - Memorandum to J. Stalin, Secretary of the TsK KPSS (copies to V. Molotov and L. Beria) from V. Potemkin (People's Commissariat of Foreign Affairs) re a request from the Lithuanian government that 14,000 Polish internees born in western Belorussia and the western Ukraine be admitted to these territories from Lithuania; draft resolution approving the request, 1939 November (Opis 58, Reel 1.1008, File 7)
    - Extract from the minutes of the TsK VKP(b) Politburo re the procedure for admitting into the USSR former servicemen from the Polish army who are natives of the western Ukraine and Belorussia, 1939 November (Opis 58, Reel 1.1008, File 8)
    - Memorandum to the Council of People's Commissars (V. Molotov) from L. Beria, People's Commissar of Internal Affairs, with a planned procedure for admitting into the USSR former servicemen from the Polish army who are natives of the western Ukraine and Belorussia, 1939 November (Opis 58, Reel 1.1008, File 9)
    - Memorandum to the TsK VKP(b) and J. Stalin from L. Beria, People's Commissar of Internal Affairs, re a proposal from the German Embassy and from the Hungarian and the Slovak missions in the Soviet Union that they hand over to the Soviet Union Polish prisoners of war who are former residents of the western Ukraine and Belorussia, 1940 April (Opis 58, Reel 1.1008, File 10)
    - Memorandum to the TsK VKP(b) and J. Stalin from L. Beria, People's Commissar of Internal Affairs, re the position of Polish and Czech prisoners of war in the Soviet Union toward participation in Polish and Czech military detachments in the war against Germany and Beria''s proposals for organizing Polish and Czech military units within the Soviet Armed Forces and for the possible commanders of the units, 1940 November (Opis 58, Reel 1.1008, File 11)
  - Opis 59
    - Memorandum to L. Ilichev, Secretary of the TsK KPSS, from S. Suvorov, Editor in Chief of Fizmatgiz (State Publishing House on Physics and Mathematics) reporting on the plan of the Pergamon Press publishing house (Great Britain) to publish a thousand-volume book series The Commonwealth and International Library of Science, Technology, and Engineering to be distributed in former colonies to aid education, denouncing the ideological character of the enterprise, and proposing measures to oppose this action by cooperative efforts of publishing houses of socialist countries; letter (in English) to S. Suvorov from R. Maxwell, Publisher, presenting the first volumes of the publication for review and advertising material, including favorable mentions from the prime ministers of India, Nigeria, Canada, Australia, Ceylon, Sierra Leone, Rhodesia, and Tanganyika and the presidents of Pakistan and Cyprus; the letter translated into Russian, 1962 May-September (Opis 59, Reel 1.1008, File 1)
    - Memorandum to the TsK KPSS from L. Shaumian, Deputy Chairman of the Academic Council of the Soviet Encyclopedia state publishing house, reporting on the publication by Pergamon Press of the book Information About the USSR, and requesting instructions for future talks with R. Maxwell [British publisher] re the books Information About Great Britain and Information About the United States, 1962 December (Opis 59, Reel 1.1008, File 2)
    - Memorandum to the TsK KPSS from A. Yegorov, Deputy Chief of the Ideology Department, and K. Bogoliubov, Head of a Sector of the same department, requesting approval of a meeting to be held in January or February 1963 between L. Shaumian, Deputy Chairman of the Academic Council of the Soviet Encyclopedia State Scientific Publishing House, and R. Maxwell [British publisher], 1962 December (Opis 59, Reel 1.1008, File 3)
    - Memorandum to the TsK KPSS from A. Yegorov, Deputy Chief of the Ideology Department, and K. Bogoliubov, Head of a Sector of the same department, presenting their opinions of the proposal of S. Suvorov, Editor in Chief of Fizmatgiz (State Publishing House on Physics and Mathematics) that Soviet publishing houses, in cooperation with publishing houses of socialist countries, publish books to be distributed in developing countries, 1963 January (Opis 59, Reel 1.1008, File 4)
    - Memorandum to the TsK KPSS from B. Burkov, Chairman of the Board of the News Publishing Agency (Agenstvo pechati Novosti - APN), re a campaign waged in Great Britain and inspired by the United States in order to prevent the conclusion of an agreement between the APN and the Daily Mirror (International Publishing Corporation) on publishing and distributing Sputnik magazine in the English-speaking countries on the ground of employment by Sputnik of K. Philby, famous Soviet spy in Great Britain, 1967 October (Opis 59, Reel 1.1008, File 5)
    - Memorandum to the TsK KPSS from B. Pankin, Chairman of the Board of the All-Union Agency on Copyright (VAAP), re publication of the book Leonid Ilyich Brezhnev: Brief Biographic Essay by the Pergamon Press publishing house (Great Britain), 1977 January (Opis 59, Reel 1.1008, File 6)
    - Memorandum to the TsK KPSS from V. Medvedev, Deputy Chief of the Propaganda Department, requesting approval for the publication of the book Leonid Ilyich Brezhnev: Brief Biographic Essay by the Pergamon Press publishing house (Great Britain); brief handwritten note dispatching the material to TsK secretaries; brief note from B. Pankin, Chairman of the Board of the All-Union Agency on Copyright (VAAP), requesting that his memorandum be sent to M. Zimianin's secretariat, January (Opis 59, Reel 1.1008, File 7)
    - Memorandum of a conversation between V. Popov, Soviet Ambassador to Great Britain, and R. Maxwell, Director of the Pergamon Press publishing house, re a Soviet proposal that Maxwell publish the book Leonid Ilyich Brezhnev: Pages of His Life, first published in 1978 by the Simon and Schuster publishing house (United States), instead of the book Leonid Ilyich Brezhnev: Brief Biographic Essay, 1981 January (Opis 59, Reel 1.1008, File 8)
    - Memorandum of a conversation between V. Bykov, Counselor and Envoy of the Soviet Embassy in Great Britain, and R. Maxwell, Director of Pergamon Press, re status of the publication by R. Maxwell of the book Leonid Ilyich Brezhnev: Pages of His Life, 1981 January (Opis 59, Reel 1.1008, File 9)
    - Memorandum of a conversation between V. Popov, Soviet Ambassador to Great Britain, and R. Maxwell, Director of Pergamon Press, re Maxwell's high-level conference with the Soviet authorities, publication by Pergamon Press of Brezhnev's memoirs and other books by Soviet leaders and of a series of annotated bibliographies on social sciences prepared in the socialist countries, and invitation to Great Britain of R. Mdivani, Chief of the Department of Scientific and Bibliographic Information of the Institute of Scientific Information on Social Sciences of the USSR Academy of Sciences, Maxwell's willingness to cooperate with Soviet publishing houses taking propaganda actions in Great Britain in anticipation of the 60th anniversary of the USSR, and publication in Great Britain of the book Modern Diplomacy of Bourgeois States with an introduction by A. Gromyko, 1982 March (Opis 59, Reel 1.1008, File 10)
    - Memorandum of a conversation between V. Popov, Soviet Ambassador to Great Britain, and R. Maxwell, Director of Pergamon Press, re the importance of representation in Great Britain of the books by Soviet leaders that are published by Pergamon Press, Maxwells impressions from N. Tikhonov(?), Maxwell's opinion on the coming conference of the leaders of seven Western countries in Versailles and the main problems to be discussed there, on the Falkland crisis, and the visit of Pope John Paul II to Great Britain, confidential information on Maxwell's plans to start publishing a labor party newspaper in Manchester, Popov's observations on the TsK KPSS Plenum and the Food Program worked out there, and Maxwell's opinion of Soviet agriculture, 1982 June (Opis 59, Reel 1.1008, File 11)
    - Memorandum to the TsK KPSS from D. Ustinov approving the publication of his book We Serve Our Motherland and Communism by the Pergamon Press publishing house, 1982 June (Opis 59, Reel 1.1008, File 12)
    - Memorandum to the TsK KPSS from K. Dolgov, Chairman of the Board of the All-Union Agency on Copyright (VAAP), re publication in Great Britain by Pergamon Press of a collection of articles and speeches of V. Grishin, Member of the TsK KPSS Politburo and Secretary of the Moscow City KPSS Committee, 1983 February (Opis 59, Reel 1.1008, File 13)
    - Memorandum to the TsK KPSS from B. Stukalin, Chief of the Propaganda Department, and V. Ignatenko, Deputy Chief of the Department of Political Propaganda Abroad, requesting approval of the publication in Great Britain by Pergamon Press of a collection of articles and speeches of V. Grishin, Member of the TsK KPSS Politburo and Secretary of the Moscow City KPSS Committee; brief handwritten note, 1983 March (Opis 59, Reel 1.1008, File 14)
    - Memorandum to the TsK KPSS from V. Yeliutin, USSR Minister of Higher and Secondary Special Education, re awarding the title Doctor honoris causa by Moscow State University to R. Maxwell, Director of the Pergamon Press publishing house, in connection with his 60th birthday, 1983 April (Opis 59, Reel 1.1008, File 15)
    - Memorandum to the TsK KPSS from S. Trapeznikov, Chief of the Department of Science and Educational Institutions, and A. Cherniaev, Deputy Chief of the International Department, requesting approval to award the title Doctor honoris causa from Moscow State University to R. Maxwell, 1983 May (Opis 59, Reel 1.1008, File 16)
    - Memorandum to the TsK KPSS from K. Dolgov, Chairman of the Board of the All-Union Agency on Copyright (VAAP), re publication in Great Britain of the second edition of the collection of works by IU. Andropov, General Secretary of the TsK KPSS and Chairman of the Presidium of the USSR Supreme Soviet; list of the works included in the said edition, 1983 July (Opis 59, Reel 1.1008, File 17)
    - Memorandum to the TsK KPSS from L. Zamiatin, Chief of the Department of Political Propaganda Abroad, and V. Zagladin, Deputy Chief of the International Department, requesting approval of the publication in Great Britain of the second edition of the collection of works by IU. Andropov, General Secretary of the TsK KPSS and Chairman of the Presidium of the USSR Supreme Soviet; brief handwritten note, 1983 July (Opis 59, Reel 1.1008, File 18)
    - Memorandum to the TsK KPSS from N. Chetverikov, Deputy Chief of the Department of Political Propaganda Abroad, V. Shaposhnikov, Deputy Chief of the International Department, and V. Zakharov, Deputy Chief of the Propaganda Department, re publication by the Pergamon Press publishing house (Great Britain) of the propaganda materials related to the 40th anniversary of V-E Day, 1984 December (Opis 59, Reel 1.1008, File 19)
    - Memorandum of a conversation between V. Popov, Soviet Ambassador to Great Britain, and R. Maxwell, Director of Pergamon Press and the Mirror newspaper group, re Maxwell's comments about answers given by K. Chernenko, General Secretary of the TsK KPSS and Chairman of the Presidium of the USSR Supreme Soviet, to questions put by a correspondent of the CAN television company with respect to military competition between the United States and the Soviet Union, Maxwell's request to interview K. Chernenko, publication by Pergamon Press of a new book by K. Chernenko, measures proposed by Maxwell for Pergamon Press in anticipation of the 40th V-E Day, and Maxwell's evaluation of the political situation in Great Britain, 1985 February (Opis 59, Reel 1.1008, File 20)
    - Memorandum to the TsK KPSS from N. Chetverikov, Chairman of the Board of the All-Union Agency on Copyright (VAAP), re publication in Great Britain of a series of collections of works by M. Gorbachev, General Secretary of the TsK KPSS and Chairman of the Presidium of the USSR Supreme Soviet, including materials on Gorbachev's summit with R. Reagan in Reykjavik, 1986 October (Opis 59, Reel 1.1008, File 21)
    - Memorandum to the TsK KPSS from IU. Skliarov, Chief of the Propaganda Department, requesting approval for publication in Great Britain of a second collection of works by M. Gorbachev, General Secretary of the TsK KPSS and Chairman of the Presidium of the USSR Supreme Soviet; brief handwritten instructions to N. Shishlin from A. N. Yakovlev, 1986 October-November (Opis 59, Reel 1.1008, File 22)